<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Dev Log | Gabriel Coelho</title><link>https://ocoelhogabriel.github.io/ogc-blog/en/post/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Dev Log | Gabriel Coelho</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ocoelhogabriel.github.io/ogc-blog/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Pragmatic Programmer: The cat ate my source code - Managing your Repository</title><link>https://ocoelhogabriel.github.io/ogc-blog/en/p/the-cat-ate-my-source-code/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ocoelhogabriel.github.io/ogc-blog/en/p/the-cat-ate-my-source-code/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ocoelhogabriel.github.io/ogc-blog/cat-963931_1280_451382982400069560.jpg"
	width="1280"
	height="857"
	loading="lazy"
	
		alt="Programming cat or a chaotic technological environment"
	
 
	
		class="gallery-image" 
		data-flex-grow="149"
		data-flex-basis="358px"
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have all been there. The deadline is bursting, a critical bug appears in the staging environment or the database gets corrupted. The instinctive reaction of many people is to look for someone to blame: &amp;ldquo;The supplier delayed&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The library has a bug&amp;rdquo;, or the classic school excuse adapted for the backend: &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;The cat ate my source code&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the difference between an ordinary developer and a &lt;strong&gt;Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/strong&gt; starts exactly here: in the technical posture regarding responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="responsibility-is-an-active-choice"&gt;&lt;a href="#responsibility-is-an-active-choice" class="header-anchor"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Responsibility is an Active Choice
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In software development, responsibility is something you actively assume. When you accept a task, define an architecture or spin up a Spring Boot service, you are committing to delivering it working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key point of item 1.1 of the book is not about having total control over the universe (we know hardware fails and Wi-Fi drops), but about how we deal with failures when they inevitably occur. A pragmatic programmer does not try to hide their mistakes under the rug or ignore technical debt. They are honest, direct, and focused on the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-cat-or-the-rubber-duck-test"&gt;&lt;a href="#the-cat-or-the-rubber-duck-test" class="header-anchor"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Cat (or the Rubber Duck) Test
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When something goes wrong, the defense instinct makes us create justifications. Before running to your tech lead and saying the server is to blame, authors Andrew Hunt and David Thomas suggest a simple mental exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;blockquote&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Before you approach anyone to tell them why something can&amp;rsquo;t be done, stop and listen to yourself. Talk to the rubber duck on your monitor or to the cat. Does your excuse sound reasonable or does it sound like amateurism?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your code disappeared because you didn&amp;rsquo;t push, the machine is not to blame. The technical responsibility was to have a secure workflow. If you didn&amp;rsquo;t have a contingency plan for a risk you knew existed, the failure is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="provide-options-dont-make-excuses"&gt;&lt;a href="#provide-options-dont-make-excuses" class="header-anchor"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Provide Options, Don&amp;rsquo;t Make Excuses
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most valuable lesson here is the mindset shift from &amp;ldquo;making excuses&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;providing options&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pragmatic programmer analyzes the incident and presents alternative solutions. Instead of just saying &amp;ldquo;the code is not ready&amp;rdquo;, try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;We won&amp;rsquo;t deliver the complete feature today, but we can deploy the MVP with endpoints X and Y and finish Z tomorrow.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The server went down, but yesterday&amp;rsquo;s backup is intact and I can restore it in 2 hours.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;We had a complex merge conflict; if I focus on this now with John&amp;rsquo;s help, we can resolve it by the end of the day.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing this, you take the focus off the failure and put it on the resolution, demonstrating control over the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ocoelhogabriel.github.io/ogc-blog/laptop-1839876_1280_4408746520264064125.jpg"
	width="1280"
	height="853"
	loading="lazy"
	
		alt="Organized work environment"
	
 
	
		class="gallery-image" 
		data-flex-grow="150"
		data-flex-basis="360px"
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="real-case-when-the-cat-actually-ate-my-code"&gt;&lt;a href="#real-case-when-the-cat-actually-ate-my-code" class="header-anchor"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Real Case: When the cat actually &amp;ldquo;ate&amp;rdquo; my code
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have experienced this exact situation. On a project where I was solely responsible for developing a new product from scratch, I ended up losing all the work done up to that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had already done the technical study, analyzed the documentation, and a large part of the main features was already running in a first test version. What I lost was not just a simple bug fix, but ready implementations, validated tests, and complex business rules that had been tailored specifically for the company&amp;rsquo;s scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And what did I do? Did I sit on the floor and cry?&lt;/strong&gt; No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went straight to my leader and played clean: I explained that I had lost the changes amid the commits and that I would need to redo the work. Since the reasoning was fresh in my memory and the architecture was already defined, I just told my leader that I would solve it, and sat down to code again. The result? The code came out much better than it was before, cleaner and more performant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, my workflow has changed. Even if it is a small adjustment to a project property, I commit it. I keep in mind that my work is only safe when it is in the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion-trust-is-built-with-honesty"&gt;&lt;a href="#conclusion-trust-is-built-with-honesty" class="header-anchor"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conclusion: Trust is Built with Honesty
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taking responsibility for failures is not a sign of weakness; it is a sign of seniority. When your colleagues know you won&amp;rsquo;t try to deceive them with creative excuses, they start to trust your technical judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time something goes wrong — and it will —, leave the cat alone. Take a deep breath, evaluate the damage, prepare viable options, and take control of your code.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>